A Finding Aid to the Coulton Waugh and Waugh Family Papers, 1751-1974, bulk 1838-1974, in the Archives of American Art aaa.waugwaug
Archives of American Art
Coulton Waugh and Waugh Family papers
bulk 1838-1974
1751-1974
aaa.waugwaug
Archives of American Art
26.9 Linear feet
The Coulton Waugh and Waugh Family papers measure 26.9 linear feet and date from 1751-1974 with the bulk of material dating from 1838 to 1974. The collection contains material from this family of artists living and working in Provincetown, Cape Cod, New York City, and England, including Coulton Waugh, Frederick Judd Waugh, Samuel Bell Waugh, and scattered material from Elizabeth Waugh, Ida Waugh, and Odin Waugh. Biographical materials, correspondence, diaries, writings, book project files, teaching files, business records, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, and artwork are found.
Waugh, Coulton, 1896-1973
Scope and Contents note
Coulton Waugh and Waugh Family papers measure 26.9 linear feet and date from 1751-1974 with the bulk of material dating from 1838 to 1974. The collection contains material from this family of artists living and working in Provincetown, Cape Cod, New York City, and England, including Coulton Waugh, Frederick Judd Waugh, Samuel Bell Waugh, and scattered material from Elizabeth Waugh, Ida Waugh, and Odin Waugh. Biographical materials, correspondence, diaries, writings, book project files, teaching files, business records, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, and artwork are found.
The Coulton Waugh papers comprise the bulk of this collection and include scattered biographical material; professional and personal correspondence concerning family, friends, arts organizations, and comics; a diary, notebooks, drafts of short stories, and other writings; book project files relating to three publications by Coulton Waugh: The Comics (1947), "Junior Editors" series, and How to Paint With a Knife (1971); teaching files from Waugh's painting classes; business records regarding the Hooked Rug and Ship Model Shop, Storm King Art Center, Hudson River Prints company, and scattered sales lists, receipts, insurance records, and leases; clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs relating to Waugh and reproductions of works of art; twenty-three daily comics scrapbooks containing clippings; scattered photographs including portraits and snapshots of Coulton Waugh, photos of buildings, and of works of art; and extensive sketchbooks as well as comic mock-ups and other original artwork by Waugh.
The Frederick Judd Waugh papers include scattered biographical materials; personal and professional correspondence, much of which relates to exhibitions, and sales; business records; drafts of Waugh's Patch Pocket Stories, and other short stories and notes; printed material relating to Waugh's career as well as souvenirs; photo albums, potraits and snapshots of Frederick Judd Waugh, and photos of works of art; and original sketches and drawings.
The Samuel Bell Waugh papers include scattered biographical materials; correspondence containing letters from artists, family and arts organizations; a 1838 diary with a transcript and writings about Waugh by others; business records; printed materials; photographs including portraits of Samuel Bell Waugh and photos of works of art; and a sketchbook, sketches and drawings, and a self-portrait.
Assorted Waugh family papers include papers of Clara Waugh, Elizabeth Waugh, Gwen Waugh, Ida Waugh, and Odin Waugh. There are also biographical sketches and genealogical writings for the Waugh family. There is correspondence of Elizabeth, Gwen and Ida Waugh; writings and notes by Elizabeth Waugh, Clara Waugh, and by others regarding the Waugh family; business records for the Waugh family and Elizabeth Waugh; printed material relating to the Waugh family; scrapbooks compiled by Elizabeth Jenkinson (mother of Elizabeth Waugh), and a travel scrapbook; photograph portraits of family members and group photos, snapshots of groups of family members, photos of Waugh family homes, exhibitions, works of art, and a photo album of works of art; artwork and artifacts including sketches by Elizabeth Waugh, Ida Waugh, Odin Waugh, and unsigned sketches.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in several installments from 1977-1983 by Odin Waugh Buchanan, Coulton Waugh's widow.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
The Waugh family consists of three generations of artists including portraitist Samuel Bell Waugh (1814-1885), landscape artist Frederick Judd Waugh (1861-1940), and cartoonist, painter, and writer Coulton Waugh (1896-1973). The family lived and worked in Provincetown, New York City, Cape Cod, and England.
Born in Pennsylvania in 1814, Samuel Bell Waugh's developed a reputation for being a portraitist in Philadelphia. He travelled to Italy in the 1840s where he spent seven years painting large panoramas. Samuel and his wife Ida had one daughter, also named Ida. Waugh's second wife Eliza studied art under her husband and produced miniture portraits. In 1861, Eliza and Samuel had one son named Frederick Judd. Samuel Bell Waugh died in 1885.
Frederick Judd Waugh attended military school but ultimately enrolled in to the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts. With his wife Eugenie (Gene), Frederick went to Europe where he settled on Sark in the Channel Islands. He painted landscape and marine scenes during his time in England. Eugenie and Frederick's son Frederick Coulton was born in Cornwall, England in 1896. Also, the couple had a daughter named Gwenyth. The family returned to the United States and settled in Cape Cod, the Maine coast, and New Jersey.
Coulton Waugh studied at the Art Students League in New York City where he sketched portraits of people he encountered on the streets. Ultimately, Coulton settled in Cape Cod with his first wife Elizabeth Jenkinson who was a writer and artist. Together, they owned a shop for model ships and hooked rugs. In the 1940s, Coulton wrote daily comic strips and in 1947 wrote a history of the medium entitled The Comics. He wrote and illustrated Dickie Dare, Hank, and Sam of the Seven C's, among others. Coulton Waugh's second wife, Odin, was an artist who illustrated some of her husband's comic strips.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 4 series.
Series 1: Coulton Waugh papers, circa 1896-1974 (Box 1-13, 20-28, 31, 33-34, 35-53, 55-56; 20 linear feet)
Series 2: Frederick Judd Waugh papers, circa 1870-1966 (Box 13-17, 28, 30, 32; 4.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Samuel Bell Waugh papers, 1838-1910 (Box 17, 26-27, 29, 54; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Assorted Waugh Family papers, 1751-1974 (Box 18-19, 30-32, 46, 49; 1.5 linear feet)
Storm King Art Center; Waugh, Elizabeth, d.1944; Waugh, Frederick Judd, 1861-1940; Waugh, Gwyneth; Waugh, Ida, d. 1919; Waugh, Odin; Waugh, Samuel Bell, 1814-1885; Artists -- United States; Cartooning; Diaries; Drawings; Painting -- Study and teaching; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Transcripts
- Coulton Waugh papers, circa 1896-1974; Series 1; 20 Linear feet Box 1-13, 20-28, 31, 33-32, 35-53, 55-56
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, book project files, teaching files, business and financial records, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, and artwork.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 10 subseries.
  1.1: Biographical Materials, circa 1914-1958
  1.2: Correspondence, 1918-1975
  1.3: Writings and Notes, 1919-1970s
  1.4: Book Project Files, circa 1940-1974
  1.5: Teaching Files, 1955-1961
  1.6: Business and Financial Records, 1923-1960
  1.7: Printed Material, 1920-1974
  1.8: Scrapbooks, 1940-1960s
  1.9: Photographs, circa 1896-circa 1940
  1.10: Artwork, circa 1910-1960s
  - Biographical Materials, circa 1914-1958; 1.1
    Scattered biographical material includes address books, identification cards, and a passport.
    - Address Books, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Certificate, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Identification Card, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Birthplace Photo, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Waugh Family History Written by Coulton Waugh, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Passport, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - World War I Material, circa 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Likely Coulton Waugh's, possibly Frederick Judd Waugh's
    - Yearbook, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1975; 1.2
    Professional and family correspondence includes incoming letters and scattered drafts of outgoing lettes. Correspondence relates to Waugh's professional and personal life and concerns his family, friends, arts organizations, and his comics. Correspondents include Gwen Waugh, Eugenie Waugh, Elizabeth Waugh, Odin Waugh, Grand Central Art Galleries, and the National Cartoonist Society among others.
    - 1910s-1920s, 1918-1922 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - 1930s, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
    - 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 17-22)
    - 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - 1960s, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
    - 1970s, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - 1930s-1970s, circa 1930-circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Writings and Notes, 1919-circa 1970s; 1.3
    There are drafts and typescripts of short stories; notes on art, the Waugh family, and boats; and notes referring to Waugh's daily plans and schedules.
    - Diary, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Notebooks, 1919-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
    - Short Stories, circa 1930-1950 (Box 2, Folder 17-23)
    - Notes, Art, circa 1920s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 24-29)
    - Notes, Art, circa 1920s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notes, Waugh Family, 1940s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
    - Notes, Boats, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notes, Daily Plans, circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notes, General, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 8-22)
  - Book Project Files, circa 1940-1974; 1.4
    Files relating to Coulton Waugh's book projects include The Comics (1947), books produced from the "Junior Editors" newspaper column, and How to Paint With a Knife (1972). Files may include drafts and manuscripts, correspondence relating to publishing, illustrations, proofs, and final copies.
    - The Comics, by Coulton Waugh, circa 1940-1945 (Box 3, Folder 23-27)
    - The Comics, by Coulton Waugh, circa 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1-14)
    - "Junior Editors," by Coulton Waugh, 1950s-1970 (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
    - "Junior Editors," by Coulton Waugh, circa 1950-1970 (Box 5, Folder 1-14)
    - "Junior Editors," by Coulton Waugh, circa 1950-1970 (Box 6, Folder 1-11)
    - How to Paint With a Knife, by Coulton Waugh, circa 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 12-15)
    - How to Paint With a Knife, by Coulton Waugh, circa 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 1-20)
    - How to Paint With a Knife, by Coulton Waugh, circa 1970-1974 (Box 8, Folder 1-13)
    - How to Paint With a Knife, by Coulton Waugh, circa 1970 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - How to Paint With a Knife, by Coulton Waugh, circa 1970 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Teaching Files, 1955-1961; 1.5
    Correspondence, grade books, student papers, teaching plans, and evaluations are from Coulton Waugh's art classes.
    - Appointment Letters, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1961 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Grade Books, 1955-1961 (Box 8, Folder 16-20)
    - Evaluations, 1955-1961 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Notebook, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Teaching Ideas File, "Dead File", 1961 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Student Papers, 1955-1961 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Business and Financial Records, 1923-1960; 1.6
    Found are records from Coulton and Elizabeth Waugh's The Hooked Rug and Ship Model Shop and the Hudson River Prints, material from Waugh's time at the Storm King Art Center, exhibition materials, sales lists, receipts, insurance documents, and leases.
    - The Hooked Rug and Ship Model Shops records, 1930-1939 (Box 9, Folder 5-13)
    - Storm King Art Center Materials, circa 1950 (Box 9, Folder 14-16)
    - Exhibition Materials, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Material on Frederick Judd Waugh's Art, circa 1950 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Sales Lists, 1930s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 19-20)
    - Receipts, 1930-1960 (Box 9, Folder 21-22)
    - Insurance Records, 1923-1948 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Leases, 1927-1952 (Box 9, Folder 24-25)
    - Hudson River Prints Records, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 26-27)
  - Printed Material, 1920-1974; 1.7
    Found are proofs for Waugh's comic strips, exhibition announcements and catalogs, reproductions of works of art, clippings, and reference material.
    - Comic Proofs, 1930s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Comic Proofs, 1930s-1970s (Box 10, Folder 1-10)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1950s-1974 (Box 10, Folder 11-16)
    - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1920-1970 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1920-1970 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
    - Clippings, 1920-1970s (Box 11, Folder 5-9)
    - Ships and Hudson River Material, 1930s (Box 11, Folder 10-12)
    - Holiday Cards, circa 1960 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Newsletters and Miscellaneous Material, 1950s (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Oversized Comic Proofs, circa 1960 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Oversized Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1930 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbooks, 1940-1960s; 1.8
    There are 23 scrapbooks of clippings of Waugh's daily comic strips.
    - Daily Comics Scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 21, Folder 1-3)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 22, Folder 1-3)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbook, 1940s (Box 54)
    - Daily Comics Scrapbook, 1940s (Box 55)
  - Photographs, circa 1896-circa 1940; 1.9
    Portraits and snapshots are of Coulton Waugh, works of art, and of buildings and landscapes. Family photos of Coulton Waugh are found in Series 4.
    - Portraits and Snapshots of Coulton Waugh, circa 1896-1940s (Box 11, Folder 15-17)
    - Buildings and Landscapes, circa 1920-1930 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Reference Photos, 1920s-1940s (Box 11, Folder 19-21)
  - Sketchbooks and Artwork, circa 1910-1960s; 1.10
    Artwork spanning Waugh's career includes extensive sketchbooks, loose sketches, prints, textiles, and mock-ups of comics by Coulton Waugh. Mock-ups for comics include the strips: Dickie Dare, Sam of the Seven C's, and Hank, among others.
    - Sketchbooks, 1918-1940s (Box 11, Folder 22-35)
    - Sketchbooks, 1918-1940s (Box 12, Folder 1-21)
    - Loose Sketches, circa 1910-1960s (Box 12, Folder 22-23)
    - Loose Sketches, circa 1910-1960s (Box 13, Folder 1-13)
    - Prints, circa 1935 (Box 13, Folder 14-15)
    - Textiles, 1950s-1960s (Box 13, Folder 16-18)
    - Oversized Sketches, circa 1940 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
    - Oversized Sketches, circa 1940 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Comic Mock-Ups, circa 1940-1965 (Box 33)
    - Oversized Sketches, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 34, Folder 1-5)
    - Comic Mock-Ups, circa 1940-1965 (Box 35)
    - Comic Mock-Ups, circa 1940-1965 (Box 36)
    - Comic Mock-Ups, circa 1940-1965 (Box 37)
    - Comic Mock-Ups, circa 1940-1965 (Box 38)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1940 (Box 39)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1940 (Box 40)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1940 (Box 41)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1940 (Box 42)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1940 (Box 43)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, Cartoons, circa 1950 (Box 44)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, Cartoons, circa 1950 (Box 45)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1940 (Box 46)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1950 (Box 47)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1950 (Box 48)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1950 (Box 49)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1950 (Box 50)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1960 (Box 51)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1960 (Box 52)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1960 (Box 53)
- Frederick Judd Waugh papers, circa 1870-1966; Series 2; 4.3 Linear feet Box 13-17, 28, 30, 32
  This series is arranged as 7 subseries.
  2.1: Biographical Materials, 1892-1941
  2.2: Correspondence, 1861-1940
  2.3: Business and Financial Records, circa 1880s-1945
  2.4: Writings and Notes, circa 1900-1940
  2.5: Printed Material, 1920-1960
  2.6: Photographs, circa 1870-1966
  2.7: Artwork, circa 1880-circa 1930
  Found are biographical materials, correspondence, business records, writings and notes, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.
  - Biographical Material, 1892-1941; 2.1
    Found are obituaries and biographical sketches, a marriage certificate, identification card, and membership materials from various organizations.
    - Biographical Sketches, Obituaries, and Memorials, 1892-1941 (Box 13, Folder 19-20)
    - Marriage Certificate, 1892 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Identification Card, 1918 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Membership Materials, 1921-1940 (Box 13, Folder 23-24)
  - Correspondence, 1861-1940; 2.2
    Found are letters from museums, galleries, companies and institutions as well as family correspondence. Included are Vose Gallery, Grand Central Gallery, the Nebraska State Normal College, the 1910 International Fine Arts Exposition, and the Bakelite corporation. Much of the correspondence relates to exhibitions, and sales. Personal correspondents include Frederick Waugh's family members and scattered friends. Some letters are illustrated.
    - from Coulton Waugh, 1926-1947 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - 1880s-1910s, 1881-1919 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - 1920s, 1920-1929 (Box 13, Folder 27-29)
    - 1930s, 1930-1940 (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
    - Circa 1880- Circa 1940 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Business and Financial Records, circa 1880-1945; 2.3
    Found are estate records, real estate records, sales, loans, bills, receipts, and tax records.
    - Will and Estate Records, 1927-1945 (Box 14, Folder 12-14)
    - Real Estate Records, 1915-1939 (Box 14, Folder 15-17)
    - Sales Records, circa 1880s-1937 (Box 14, Folder 18-21)
    - Loan Receipts, circa 1920 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1920-1940s (Box 14, Folder 23-26)
    - Tax Records, 1919-1938 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Writings and Notes, circa 1900-1940; 2.4
    Found are drafts of Waugh's Patch Pocket Stories and other short stories; poetry; travel journals; and notes on subjects such as art, philosophy and religion.
    - Patch Pocket Stories, circa 1920 (Box 14, Folder 28-33)
    - Patch Pocket Stories, circa 1920 (Box 15, Folder 1-17)
    - "Sea Painting," by Frederick Judd Waugh, circa 1930 (Box 15, Folder 18-19)
    - "In the Days of Tell," by Frederick Judd Waugh, circa 1934 (Box 15, Folder 20-21)
    - "Eat One Eat All," by Frederick Judd Waugh, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - "Golden Whale," by Frederick Judd Waugh, circa 1930 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - "Anatomy of the Sea," by Frederick Judd Waugh, circa 1930 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Short Stories, circa 1940 (Box 15, Folder 25-26)
    - Poetry, circa 1920-1930 (Box 15, Folder 27-28)
    - General Writings, on Art, Philosophy, and Religion, circa 1910-1940 (Box 16, Folder 1-13)
    - Notebooks and Travel Journals, 1930-1940 (Box 16, Folder 14-16)
    - Notes, circa 1900-1930s (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Lists of Works of Art, 1929-1938 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Printed Material, 1920-circa 1960; 2.5
    Found are exhibition announcements and catalogs; clippings; press releases; various arts publications; and travel material such as souvenirs and maps.
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1920s-1960s (Box 16, Folder 19-22)
      Includes writings by Frederick Judd Waugh
    - Clippings, 1920-1940 (Box 16, Folder 23-24)
    - Press Releases, 1938-circa 1960 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Art Publications, 1932-1933 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Travel Material, circa 1930s (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - Photographs, circa 1870-1966; 2.6
    Found are photo albums, potraits and snapshots of Frederick Judd Waugh, and photos of works of art. Researchers should note that family photos of Frederick Judd Waugh are found in Series 4.
    - Photo Album, circa 1900 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Portraits and Snapshots of Frederick Judd Waugh, circa 1870-circa 1930 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Works of Art, circa 1900-circa 1940 (Box 16, Folder 29-32)
    - Photo Album, 1910s-1920; 1966 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, circa 1880-circa 1930; 2.7
    Found are sketches and drawings.
    - Sketches and Drawings, circa 1880-circa 1930 (Box 16, Folder 33-36)
    - Sketches and Drawings, circa 1880-circa 1930 (Box 17, Folder 1-27)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1910 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1945 (Box 30, Folder 1)
- Samuel Bell Waugh papers, 1838-1910; Series 3; 1 Linear feet Box 17, 26-27, 29, 54
  3.1: Biographical Materials, 1848-circa 1860
  3.2: Correspondence, 1838-1885
  3.3: Writings and Notes, 1838-circa 1900
  3.4: Business and Financial Records, 1841-1884
  3.5: Printed Material, 1840-1884
  3.6: Photographs, 1880-1910
  3.7: Artwork, 1840-1880s
  This series contains biographical material, correspondence, writings and notes, business records, printed material, photographs, and artwork.
  - Biographical Materials, 1848-circa 1860; 3.1
    Found are membership certificates and a fragment of a book spine.
    - Membership Certificates, 1848-1849 (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - Book Spine, circa 1860 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1838-1885; 3.2
    Found are scattered letters from artists, family and arts organizations. Correspondents include George Childs, James Claghorn, Lydia Cope, F. O. C. Darley, Theodore Duclère, John Francis, Henry Reed, the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, and the 1850 and 1877 International Expositions.
    - 1830s-1880s, 1838-1885 (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - Writings and Notes, 1838-circa 1900; 3.3
    Found are writings including a 1838 diary with a transcript and writings about Samuel Bell Waugh by others.
    - Diary and Transcript, 1838-circa 1900 (Box 17, Folder 31-32)
    - Writings about Samuel Bell Waugh by Others, circa 1850 (Box 17, Folder 33)
  - Business and Financial Records, 1841-1884; 3.4
    Found are ledgers and a receipt.
    - Ledgers, 1842-1884 (Box 17, Folder 34-35)
    - Receipt, 1841 (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - Printed Material, 1840-1880; 3.5
    Found are clippings, an exhibition catalog, travel materials from Italy, and reference material.
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1866 (Box 17, Folder 37)
    - Clippings, 1840-1865 (Box 17, Folder 38)
    - Travel Material, circa 1840 (Box 17, Folder 39)
    - Reference Material, 1880 (Box 17, Folder 40)
  - Photographs, 1880-1910; 3.6
    Found are portraits of Samuel Bell Waugh and photos of works of art. Researchers should note that family photos of Samuel Bell Waugh are found in Series 4.
    - Portraits of Samuel Bell Waugh, 1880 (Box 17, Folder 41)
    - Works of Art, circa 1910 (Box 17, Folder 42-44)
  - Artwork, 1840-1880s; 3.7
    Found are artworks including a sketchbook, loose sketches and drawings, a self-portrait, and albums containing sketches and drawings.
    - Sketchbook, 1840 (Box 17, Folder 45)
    - Loose Sketches, 1840s-1880s (Box 17, Folder 46-54)
    - Self-Portrait, circa 1840 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Albums of Sketches and Drawings, circa 1840 (Box 27, Folder 3-4)
    - Oversized Sketches and Drawings, circa 1840 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Sketchbook, circa 1840 (Box 54)